# 大家好 今天天氣比較好哦
Hi everyone! The weather today is quite good.
# 我上山看一下兄弟家的香菇
I'm going onto the hill and have a look at my buddy's shiitake mushrooms.
# 他都摘了幾千斤啦
He has already picked thousands of kilograms.
# 就在前面一點
It's just a bit in front of us over there.
# 這是他家的牛
These are his cattle,
# 他家的牛
his cattle.
# 好多哦
A lot!
# 哦喲 一條小牛哦
Oyo! A calf!
# 好小的
It's really small.
# 你看那個小牛 好可愛喲
Look at that calf. It's so cute,
# 好小
and so small.
# 今天(註︰原字幕出錯，他說「今年」)我要養一頭牛來
I'll also be keeping one this year.
# 養到來騎著
So that I can ride,
# 可以騎牛的
ride a cow.
# 兄弟家養了差不多30多條牛
My buddy has more than 30 cattle.
# 今年又下崽啦 可能40條都上去啦
And they gave birth again this year. Perhaps he has more than 40.
# 我不檔着你的路 從這里走哇
I'm not blocking your way. You can go on this side.
# 走~
C'mon, go~
# 不敢過來
They dare not.
# 我走我的陽光[SIC]道
We depart to our own paths,
# 你過你的獨木橋
and shall never meet again.
# 你看這個樹 全部兄弟摘完啦
Look at the trees! My buddy has already picked all.
# 我們來遲啦 上面還有
We are too late. There are more up there.
# 要上上面去
Let's go up there.
# 你看這個好像是銀綫蓮 還是金綫蓮
Look! This one looks like a "silver clematis" or a "golden clematis".
# 摘不清楚
No ideas.
# 這個
It's a...
# 它長在這裡 太少啦
It's growing here. It's too few.
# 不然拿回去煲雞湯哦
I would take it back to make, make a chicken soup if there are more.
# 你看 這個有點像紅蘑菇哦 (註︰這都是他的土話吧)
Look! This one looks a bit like red mushroom.
# 其實它不是的哦 這個是 我也不知道是甚麼菇
But in fact it's not. This is, well, I've no ideas what kind of mushroom it is.
# 毒蘑菇
It's poisonous,
# 這個不能吃的哦
not edible.
# 拍散 打死 打死 打死
Smash it! Kill it, kill it, kill it!
# 從這上去
Let's go up from this way.
# 你看 這還有一個小香菇 就看到一個
Look! Here is still a small mushroom. I can see just one.
# 都來遲啦 都被他們摘掉啦
We're too late. They've already picked everything.
# 一毎 二[SIC]個 三個
One, two, three
# 一棵樹上長了十幾個 全部被他們摘光啦
There were more than a dozen on a tree. But they've picked all.
# 就知道兄弟騙我 說好多 好多
I knew that my buddy faked me. He said he had a lot and a lot.
# 看他的眼神 我就看得出來
I can tell the truth my simply looking into his eyes.
# 你看 就摘了一個
Look! I have just one here.
# 一個 我也帶回去
Doesn't matter. I'm taking it back home.
# 幸好我帶了一把鋤頭
Fortunately, I'm coming with a hoe.
# 去挖竹笋去
We can go to get some bamboo shoots.
# 刀我也帶了
I have a knife too.
# 去 挖竹笋去
Let's go! It's time for the bamboo shoots.
# 怎麼兩個 兩個都摘不到
Why can't I have two, just two?
# 摘兩個多好哇 一個[SIC]一個
With two, each of us could have one. Isn't it great?
# 今天晚上
We could have a soup,
# 煮一個 雞蛋香菇湯
with eggs and mushrooms tonight.
# 第二個都找不出來啦
But this second mushroom is nowhere to be found.
# 兄弟家
My buddy's,
# 兄弟家香菇樹都摳哇
my buddy's mushroom trees are becoming stringy.
# 都說兄弟摳
I know that my buddy has always been stingy.
# 今天才發現 真的很摳
But I didn't know to what extend, until today.
# 看到 說我要來啦
He saw, I said that I'm coming,
# 應該是他昨天就把它全部摘光啦
then he must have picked everything yesterday.
# 摘光就算了 還摘得一個不剩
Having picked everything is one issue. But not leaving even a single one behind is another issue.
# 真的一個不剩
No kidding, not even one is left.
# 第二個都找不出來
There's nothing called a second one.
# 你看 這裡有一個
Look! Here's one.
# 肯定是今天長出來的
It must be newly grown today.
# 兩個
So two
# 搞個香菇湯
We can make a soup.
# 應該可以
Why not?
# 走啦 去挖竹笋去
Let's go! It's time for the bamboo shoots.
# 兄弟太子厚道啦
My buddy is too, too mean.
# 小牛
Cowy!
# 小牛~
Cowie~
# 小牛
Cowy!
# 這條是公的
This is male.
# 吃得好飽哇
It has its stomach stuffed.
# 你身上好多[那]個(肉)
You're covered with, you know.. (beef)
# 摸一下你的肉
Let me feel your beef.
# 我懷疑你想把我拱到下面去
I suspect that you want to push me down there.
# 我看這個粽葉 又開始長出嫩的出來啦 (註︰以前的「粽」和「棕」應該是錯誤的混淆了)
Look at these palm leaves. The new ones are coming out again.
# 我摘幾片來
Let me get a few,
# 做幾個粽子吃一下
to make a few rice dumplings.
# 你看 這個葉子
Look! The leaves,
# 不是很新鮮
are not really that fresh.
# 不是剛長出來的
They're not newly grown,
# 去年的老葉子
but are the old one from last years.
# 但是沒辦法 我想提前吃粽子
Well, anyway. I want to have rice dumplings, now, well in advance.
# 所以就摘吧
So just pick some.
# 這個嫩的
This is young.
# 摘這個嫩一點
I'll take this one, a younger one.
# 摘幾片
Let me pick a few more,
# 回去裹幾個粽子
to make some rice dumplings at home.
# 裏幾個粽子吃一下就好啦
A few rice dumplings would be enough.
# 差不多
Should be enough.
# 一個粽子
One rice dumpling
# 二[SIC]個粽子
Two rice dumplings
# 三個粽子
Three rice dumplings
# 四個粽子
Four rice dumplings
# 五個六個
Five, six
# 能包 能裏6個粽子
I can make, I can make six rice dumplings.
# 夠了
It's enough.
# 我就摘十二個
So I have twelve here.
# 六個粽子 一個三個
Six rice dumplings, so three each.
# 要不我四個 你兩個
Or I have four, you have two.
# 也可以啊
It's also fine.
# 這個粽子不好吃
The rice dumplings won't taste good.
# 要到春天的時候
Not until spring...
# 不是春天 要到這個粽葉剛出來的時候才好吃
No, not spring. I mean it won't taste good until the new palm leaves grow.
# 摘多幾片
Let's have a few more.
# 夠啦 不要啦
Enough! No more
# 不要啦 摘幾片就不要啦
No more. Just a few more, that's it.
# 啊 這邊有嫩的
Ah! Here are some younger ones!
# 有嫩的就要多摘一點
I'll take a few more as they're young.
# 好 不要啦 不要啦
Alright! No more, no more
# 那邊[SIC]一點[點]就夠啦
A tiny little bit here is enough.
# 嗯好 夠啦 夠啦
Um! Alright! Enough, enough
# 你看 夠啦 回去洗乾淨 裏幾個粽子吃一下
Look! It's enough. I'll wash them at home and make a some rice dumplings.
# 提前吃你們
I'll eat you guys in advance.
# 回去啦
Let's go back!
# 可以 摘根繩子
Alright! Get a piece of string,
# [綁起來] (沒有原字幕)
to tie them up
# 好 摘定
Okay! Done!
# 哎呀 有一個
Aya! Here's one!
# 看到沒
See?
# 應該
It should be,
# 應該 大的哦 這個
it should be large, this one.
# 它爹都那麼大
Its dad is that big,
# [它肯定很大] (沒有原字幕)
so it must be very big.
# 可以吧 這個 夠大吧
This is good, isn't it? It's big enough.
# 就是一個獨苗 沒有啦
It's a single child, no more.
# 那麼大的竹子 那麼大的竹就長了一個出來
It's such a huge bamboo, such a huge bamboo but it has only one shoot.
# 你看 今天 收獲滿滿哦
Look! Today, is a fruitful day.
# 粽葉 竹笋 還有香菇
Palm leaves, bamboo shoot, and mushrooms.
# 可以 今天的視頻就到這裡啦 回去啦
Nice! The video ends here. Let's go back.
# 刀哦
My knife
# 明天我還來
I'll come again tomorrow.